The encoder inputs the first a into I, searches and finds a in the dictionary.
It inputs the next a but finds that Ix, which is now aa, is not in the dictionary.
The encoder thus adds string aa to the dictionary as entry 256 and outputs the
token 97 (a). Variable I is initialized to the second a. The third a is input, so Ix is
the string aa, which is now in the dictionary. I becomes this string, and the fourth
a is input. Ix is now aaa which is not in the dictionary. The encoder thus adds
string aaa to the dictionary as entry 257 and outputs 256 (aa). I is initialized to
the fourth a. Continuing this process is straightforward.
The result is that strings aa, aaa, aaaa,... are added to the dictionary as
entries 256, 257, 258,... , and the output is
97 (a), 256 (aa), 257 (aaa), 258 (aaaa),...
The output consists of pointers pointing to longer and longer strings of as. The first
k pointers thus point at strings whose total length is 1 + 2 + ··· + k = (k + k2)/2.
Assuming an input stream that consists of one million as, we can find the size
of the compressed output stream by solving the quadratic equation (k + k2)/2 =
1000000 for the unknown k. The solution is k ≈ 1414. The original, 8-million bit
input is thus compressed into 1414 pointers, each at least 9-bit (and in practice,probably 16-bit) long. The compression factor is thus either 8M/(1414×9) ≈ 628.6
or 8M/(1414 × 16) ≈ 353.6.
This is an impressive result but such input streams are rare (notice that this
particular input can best be compressed by generating an output stream containing
just “1000000 a”, and without using LZW).